Guide to the Max Shachtman Papers TAM.103
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Additional information and references can be found in the following three linked Appendices:
Appendix A
includes a partial index to names and subjects, contains references for individuals which may be to correspondence, and/or to writings by or about that individual.
Appendix B
includes a partial index to pseudonyms that may appear in the Shachtman Papers.
Appendix C
includes a partial index to abbreviations that may appear in the Shachtman Papers.
Series Descriptions
Series I. Groups with which Shachtman was Affiliated; documents Shachtman's political odyssey as seen through the records of each group to which he belonged: the early American Communist Party, the Socialist Workers Party, the Workers Party, the Independent Socialist League, and the Socialist Party. Series I thus provides the needed chronology, vocabulary, and structure for understanding the remainder of the Collection. The records document the leadership activities of each group, and, of special interest, American relations with Trotsky and the world Trotskyist movement from 1928 40. While many of the group documents have been published elsewhere, others are quite rare or appear here in original drafts and hand scripts.
Series I. is organized into ten subseries:
Missing Title
A. The Communist International and the Soviet Union (1922-30)
B. The American Communist Party (Workers Party of America) (1924-28)
C. Leon Trotsky (1927-40; 1907, 1923, 1962): Writings (in Russian), Correspondence, Manuscripts, Notes and Articles on Trotsky (Dewey Commission, attempts to obtain permanent residence, assassination)
D. The International Left Opposition and Fourth International (1927-50): Official bodies of the International Sections of the International (by country or region other than the United States), Individuals
E. American left wing opposition: Communist League of America (1929-37)
F. Workers Party U.S. (Trotskyist) and entry into Socialist Party (1934-37)
G. Socialist Workers Party (includes debates with Shachtman tendency), (1934-40)
H. Workers Party (including unity talks with SWP, C.L.R. James, and Raya Dunayevskaya), (1940-50)
I. Independent Socialist League (1949-58)
J. Socialist Party (Social Democratic Federation, Democratic Socialists, Young People's Socialist League, Michael Farrington, Norman Thomas; debated issues of Cuba, Vietnam, strategies for the 60's) (1958-72).
Series II. Research Notes for The History of the Communist International; which has not been microfilmed, is devoted to Shachtman's research materials for a history of the Communist International, which he never completed, and is organized into four subseries:
Missing Title
A. By country or region
B. By topic
C. By name of author (reprints from American Slavic and East European Review)
D. Alleged materials of the Politburo (translated and evaluated by Loventhal)
Most of his notes are derived from published sources (many of which were part of his library). Citations include unusual bibliographic sources, translations from Polish, Russian, and Scandinavian language sources, personal accounts and data recollected by former participants in the Communist International. The coverage is extensive, taking in dozens of countries, political formations, and individuals. Included are handwritten notes and some clippings, articles, translated abstracts, and correspondence, giving bibliographic citations and data on the Communist International and Communist parties world wide.
Series III. Correspondence (bulk 1950s-1960s), which has been microfilmed, comprises individual correspondence, generally non official and personal, but often related to the subjects of Series I and II, and is organized into four subseries:
Missing Title
A. Individuals
B. Countries (including nationals in exile)
C. Topics
D. Publishers.
Correspondents include individual comrades and co-thinkers, friends and acquaintances in academia, publishing, and socialist groups. Some of the more significant correspondents include: Norman Thomas eliciting Shachtman's viewpoint on Leninism; Michael Harrington on the radical movement of the 1960's; Natalia Sedova Trotsky on the affairs of Trotsky's estate and on her political evolution; Erich From and A.J. Muste on the regrouping of socialists in the late 1950's; young colleagues in the ISL and Socialist Party; and international correspondents discussing changes within the world socialist movement.
Other notable correspondents include: Farrell Dobbs, Hal Draper, Raya Dunayevskaya, James T. Farrell, Ruth Fischer, Pierre Frank, Al Glotzer, Darlington Hoopes, Irving Howe, Sara Jacobs (companion to Natalia Sedova Trotsky), Julius Jacobson, Isaac Don Levine, Tom Kahn, Ernest Rice McKinney, David McReynolds, Max Nomad, Leon Sedov, Ignazio Silone, Don Slaiman, Boris Souvarine, Irwin Suall, Thomas Stamm, Esteban Volkov, Stanley Weir, B.J. Widick, Karl A. Wittfogel, and Bertram Wolfe.
Series IV. Writings and Topical Files; covers a potpourri of topical interests. Here are portions of Shachtman's manuscripts, manuscripts by others, articles and clippings which interested him (though not having the same cohesion as his research notes and clippings in Series II). Of special note are a few of the unpublished manuscripts by other authors. Alfred Rosmer's memoirs of John Reed, an outstanding example, does not appear to have been published.
Series IV is organized into five subseries, of which only subseries D: Max Shachtman Manuscripts and Other notes has been microfilmed:
Missing Title
A. Political Affairs, International (by countries or regions, topics)
B. Political Affairs, United States (groups, topics, individuals)
C. Manuscripts by others
D. Max Shachtman manuscripts and notes
E. Clippings, articles about Max Shachtman.
Series V. International Bulletins, Periodicals and other Documents; is essentially an appendix of internal publications and leaflets relating to the activities of Series I, particularly prior to 1948. These materials, prepared and circulated within each political group, are often quite rare and fragile. An invaluable collection of German leaflets traces the debate between the Nazis, the Communist Party, the Social Democrats, and the German Trotskyists in a section entitled "Hitler's Rise to Power, 1931 32." The propaganda war was deadly serious and graphic in every sense of the word. Cartoons and lithographs form the last part of Series V.
Series V is organized into five subseries, and has been microfilmed:
Missing Title
A. Left Opposition bulletins (other than United States) (1930-62)
B. Internal bulletins of U.S.A. groups (1933-67)
C. Periodicals of the Left Opposition (1928-62)
D. Hitler's Rise to Power (1931-33) (statements and periodicals)
E. Graphic Materials; "missing pages."
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically.
The papers are arranged in five series:
Missing Title
I. Groups with which Shachtman was affiliated
II. Research notes for The History of the Communist International
III. Correspondence
IV. Writings and Topical Files
V. International Bulletins, Periodicals and other Documents.
VI. Addendum
VII. Addendum 2 (unprocessed)
Related Archival Materials
"Reminiscences of Max Shachtman: Oral History" (1965) held at Columbia University Butler Library, NXCP87-A1246.
Guide published in New York University Bulletin of the Tamiment Institute/Ben Josephson Library, No. 50, April, 1983.
The George Breitman Papers (Tamiment 169)
Separated Material
The Max Shachtman Photographs (Tamiment Photographs 087).
The Max Shachtman Book, Pamphlet and Periodical Collection, has been integrated into the Tamiment Library's book, vertical file, and periodical collections, described below. (A list of these materials is held by the Library).
The Shachtman Library holdings numbered over 3000 books, over 1000 pamphlets, and 350 periodical and proceedings titles. These include rare pamphlets from Germany 1918-19, proceedings of dozens of Communist and Trotskyist sections around the world (France, Germany, Latin America), Trotskyist periodicals of many countries, and pamphlets and booklets on dozens of subjects (catalogued now in the Tamiment's vertical files). Shachtman was an earnest bibliophile with an intense interest in questions international and historical. The total collection traces the course of socialist ideas, Marxian theory, and labor history. The books include an almost comprehensive set of publications on the Communist International, numerous works on labor history, social movements in Europe, Asia, and the Americas, all the works by Lenin and Trotsky available in English and German during Shachtman's lifetime. Several original 19th century editions are included; a collection of Marx-Engels Gesamte Ausgabe in 10 volumes; 12 volumes of the writings of Ferdinand La Salle; the literary criticism of Franz Mehring; Die Neue Zeit, the magazine of the German social democracy as edited by Karl Kautsky; the French editions of the correspondence between Friedrich Engels and Paul and Laura Marx LaFargue. Many of the books were acquired as gifts and loans.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the microfilmed version, with the exception of Series II; Series IV: Parts A, B, C, and E; Series V: Part E; and Series VI. Microfilm call number is Film R-7203, Reels 1-71.
Clippings (information artifacts); Bulletins.; Lithographs.; Caricatures and cartoons.; Socialism -- United States.; Communism -- United States.; Manuscripts for publication.; Frank, Pierre; Fischer, Ruth, 1895-; Hoopes, Darlington, 1896-; Jacobs, Sara; Fromm, Erich, 1900-1980; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; Howe, Irving.; Levine, Isaac Don, 1892-1981; Jacobson, Julius; Kahn, Tom.; McReynolds, David.; Workers Party (1940-1949); McKinney, Ernest Rice, 1886-1984.; Robbins, Jack Alan.; Wolfe, Bertram David, 1896-1977.; Dunayevskaya, Raya; Draper, Hal; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979; Weir, Stan; Reed, John, 1884-1968; Nomad, Max; Rosmer, Alfred.; Trotskaia, Nataliia Ivanovna, 1882-1962.; Socialist Workers Party; Glotzer, Albert, 1908-1999.; Socialist Party (U.S.); Widick, B. J.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Wittfogel, Karl August, 1896-1988.; Communist Party of the United States of America; Stamm, Thomas; Suall, Irwin.; Independent Socialist League; Volkov, Esteban.; Sedov, Leon.; Dobbs, Farrell; Slaiman, Donald, 1919-; Souvarine, Boris.; Harrington, Michael, 1928-1989; Silone, Ignazio, 1900-1978; Muste, Abraham John, 1885-1967.; Eastman, Max, 1883-1969; Communist International; Shachtman, Yetta Barsh
- Series I: Groups with which Shachtman was affiliated (microfilmed)
  - PART A: THE COMMUNIST INTERNATIONAL AND THE SOVIET UNION
    - The Second and Third Internationals and the Vienna Union, statement, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
      General note
      Microfilm Reel Number 1
    - Communist International - session of the Bolshevization Commission - (Protocol #1), Feb 6, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 1B)
    - Communist International - discussion of the Draft Program, Sixth Congress, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Communist Party, Soviet Union (CPSU) - resolution of the Central Committee and Chinese Communist Party on situation in the party, Apr 23, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - CPSU - letter from Radek to Clara Zetkin (in German), ca.1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lenin School (Moscow) Study Guides (for English Sector) - Political Economy - Leninism - History of the Party - History of the Labor Movement in the West Dialectic Materialism, the Study of Classes, Class Strugge and Society - Economic Policy - International Trade Unionism - The History of the Labor Movement - Theses and Resolutions - Party Structure - World Economy - World Economy (in Russian), 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5-16)
  - PART B: THE AMERICAN COMMUNIST PARTY (WORKERS PARTY OF AMERICA)
    - Controversial question in the Workers Party, ca.1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - The Right Danger in the American Party, Jul 1925 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Communication to American Commission of Comintern, Nov 26, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Attempts at Unification of factions, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Answer to Bedacht's charge that Foster is non-Marxian by A. Bittelman, ca.1926 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Microfilm Reel Number 2
    - Weinstone's speech under political Committee report by Lovestone, May 27, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Telegrams to and from Moscow, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Factional discussion around American question, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Letter from Foster (1) to members of his faction, ca.1927 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Controversy in CPSU (speaker's outline), Bertram Wolf, Pres. of Agitprop Department, ca.1927 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Communication from American delegates to Comintern, Jun 26, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Political Committee, hearing (#63), Oct 27, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Statement to the Political Committee to Cannon, Shachtman, Abern, with letter to members, Oct 27, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Political Committee hearing (#63) (Trotskyist development in Finnish section), Nov 2, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Study Guide to 6 lectures by Bittelman "History of Communist Movement in America", 1929 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Independent Communist League (Boston), Bulletin #1, Dec 1928 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Outline of Party History for Discussion on 10th Anniversary, Sep 1929 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - PART C: LEON TROTSKY Writings by Trotsky (Russian Transcripts)
    - Archives' Translation of Russian language titles for folders 2-39 (prepared by George Saunders of Path finder Press), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - The Degeneration of the Bolshevik Party, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letter from Sara (Weber) Jacobs, Mar 28, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Postcard to Shachtman, signed MN (?) Istanbul, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - It is necessary to rebuild the Communist Party and the International, Jul 15, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - It is no longer possible to remain in the same International with Stalin, etc., Jul 20, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Even slander should make sense, Apr 1933 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The Chinese question after the Sixth Congress, Oct 4, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Isn't it time to understand, May 26, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Hankow to Moscow, May 28, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Second speech on the China question, ca.1928 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Chen Tu Siuls speech on the tasks of the Chinese Communist Party, ca.1927 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - The Chinese Revolution and Stalin's Thesis, May 7, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - An Inevitable Final Flourish, May 17, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - The Strangled Revolution, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - On the Revolution and its Stranglers, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Sure Road, May 11, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Against National Communism: lessons of the Red referendum, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - (not translated), 1931 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Stalin and his Agabekov, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Permanent Revolution, ca.1931 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Toward Capitalism or Socialism, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - What the Wretches' Trial teaches us, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - What next? On the campaign against the Right, ca.1929 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - A Bloc of Lefts and Rights, ca.1931 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Political contortions of the Capitalists (from a letter), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Text for a questionnaire for Those Who Recanted, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - The turn of the Communist International and the situation in Germany, ca.1930 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - A Total Collectivization District, Apr 11, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - To the Communists of China and the World: Tasks and Perspectives of the Chinese Revolution, ca.1930 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Letters of a Soviet Worker to oppositionist friend in Internal Exile, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Statement of Exiled oppositionists to Presidency Committee of the 16th Congress of CPSU, ca.1930s (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Letter #1 to all sections of the International Left Opposition, Jun 21, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - The mistakes of the Right elements of the League on the Trade Union question, Jan 4, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Letter #2 to all sections of the International Left Opposition, Jun 29, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Microfilm Reel Number 3
    - The New Zig Zag and New Dangers, Jul 15, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - On the Defenders' of the October Revolution, Jun 10, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Letter to the International Secretariat (portion), 1931 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Letter to the International Secretariat on Social Fascism' (portion), Jun 27, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence with International Secretariat and other leading International bodies (in English, German, French, Russian), 1930-1936 (Box 2, Folder 40-44)
    - Correspondence with CLA/TATUS leadership (folder 48A see also:, 1930-1940 (Box 2, Folder 45-48)
    - Copies of Max Shachtman Correspondence during Trotsky's exile period (these documents were a gift to the Tamiment Library from John F. Dwyer, 7/25/1979), 1930-1933 (Box 2, Folder 48B)
    - M.S. correspondence with L.T. and secretaries (except 1934), 1930-1940 (Box 2, Folder 49-56)
    - L.T. telegrams to and from M.S., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - L.T. correspondence (not with M.S.) (some in German, French, English) (except 1935), 1929-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
      Microfilm Reel Number 4 (begins with folder 7 of the 11 above)
    - L.T. Manuscript Section "N' to be inserted in P. 241 of the Real Situation in Russia (folders 12-34A are L.T. Manuscripts), undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Microfilm Reel Number 4
    - pp. 26-39 undated and untitled (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - L.T. speech before the Tsarist Court (at trial of Soviet Deputies), Oct 4, 1907-Oct 17, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - The Letter on the New Course (sent by L.T. to C.C. of CPSU), Dec 1923 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Trotsky's speech on the Polish Commission of July 2, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Trotsky's struggle for Leninism. in Russia, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Trotsky's second speech at the Central Commission (attached note), Jul 1927 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Trotsky is expelled from Central Committee - speech delivered at Plenary Session, Oct 23, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - On the New Stage (different translation published in Challenge of t e Left Opposition 1926-27, 2nd volume), Dec 1927 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Erklarung anden 6. Welt-Kongreso Komintern, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - The Crisis in the International, statement addressed to 6th Congress of C.I., 1928 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - The Crisis in the International (note on last page by translator L. Martel), Jul 12, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Preface: The Revolution Disfigured, May 1, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - The reply to a well-wishing contradiction (explanatory note attached), undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - A Sorry Document (may be Trotsky's own translation as an English lesson done in 1939 in Mexico), Jul 27, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Where Tbes the Leninbund road lead to? (in French), Sep 19, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Trotsky on the Labor Party Question (for the New Militant, May 19, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - It is impossible to remain in the same International as Stalin, Manouilsky, Losovsky, and Co. (in French, English; original Russian in Box 2, folder 6), Jul 20, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - It is necessary to drive the Bureaucracy and the New Aristocracy out of the Soviets (concerning the draft of the transition program of the F.I.), Jul 4, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - A Petty Bougeois Opposition in the SWP (with cover letter by Joseph Hansen dated 12/5/39), 1939 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Victor Serge refutes in his turn, Sep 7, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - The USSR in War (literal translation), Sep 25, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - On the question of the defense of the Soviet Union, Sep 26, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - On the thesis "Unity and the Youth" Notes and articles on Leon Trotsky, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 34A)
    - A. Glotzer's notes on discussion with L.T., Nov 17, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - A. Swabeck's notes on discussion with L.T., Feb 28, 1933-Mar 4, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - A. Swabeck's notes on discussion with L.T. (German), Feb 27, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Notes on discussion with L.T., Mar 24, 1938-Mar 25, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Leon Trotsky on the Jewish question (clipping in Yiddish), undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - E. Robertson conversations with L.T. on I.L.P. entry in British Labor Party, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Conversations with Crux (L.T.) on death agony of Capitalism and Labor Party, May 1938 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - M.S. notes on Trotsky work (from Buyakoda), 1933 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      Microfilm Reel Number 5
    - M.S. correspondence about L.T. (telegraph from Held), 1937 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Interview with M.S. by Florence Lehman on Radio WCCO, Minneapolis about L.T., ca.1937 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - M.S., Solow, Dewey correspondence Re: Commission Report, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - The Man Trotsky by Rae Spiegel (Raya Dunayevskaya, L.T.'s secretary and translator), 1937 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Open letter on the Siguedros Case (attempt toassassinate L. T., May 24, 1940), May 1962 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - PART D: THE INTERNATIONAL LEFT OPPOSITION AND FOURTH INTERNATIONAL
    - Mulhouse Congress - Stenogram of 2nd Session (of the SFIO (French SP) held after Stalin-Laval Pact; the Bolshevik/ Leninists had 3 delegates), Jun 9, 1935-Jun 12, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Formation of an International Organization to unite the Left Opposition (German; also note in French re: enclosed item dated 11/25/30), Oct 12, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Report of the Enlarged Bureau meeting of the organization for a Fourth International, Amsterdam, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Movement for a Fourth International (French), 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - International Communist League (ICL) (LO) Plenum and (International Secretaries) Mfinutes (folder 5 contains extracts from minutes 8/24/33 and minutes Nov.18,19,1933; folder 6 contains minutes Oct.16,1934 in French and English), 1931-1934 (Box 4, Folder 5-10)
    - Rapport d'Activite du S.I. de la L.C.I. (Bolshevik/Leninist), Sep 1933-Mar 1934 (Box 4, Folder 10A)
    - I.S. Minutes (in French), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Movement for the F.S.-I.S. or International Bureau (in French), 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - I.C.L. International News and Notes, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 13A)
    - Correspondence of I.S. or I.B. (all folders except 16 and 17 are in French and German), 1930-1935 (Box 4, Folder 14-19)
      Microfilm Reel Number 5, Microfilm Reel Number 6 (begins with folder 18, above)
    - Nbvement of the F.I. Correspondence of the I.S. and I.B. (French, German; see also: Box 5/14), 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
      Microfilm Reel Number 6
      Note: folders are out of order on this reel of film.
    - I.C.L. Conference of Four, Dec 30, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Microfilm Reel Number 6. Note: folders are out of order on this reel of film.
    - International Left Opposition - Resolutions and Statements (French, English), ca.1936 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Letter from Moscow (German), early1930s (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Excerpts from "Die Niuwe Fakkel" about Spain and Brussels (German Translation), Oct 1936 (Box 4, Folder 24A)
    - Letter from Barcelona - critique of POUM (in French), Jan 23, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 24B)
    - First International Conference of the F.I.: "Geneva" Pre Conference Theses and Resolutions, Jul 1936Aug 1936 (Box 4, Folder 25)